Guide to the Eugène and Maria Jolas Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Maria Jolas - Correspondence, 1935-1986; Series VII; 4.5; (11 boxes)
  - GENERAL
    - Greenfield, Howard
      See: Orion Press, Box 35 folder 729
    - Groden, Michael, 1976 (Box 31, Folder 624)
    - Guest, Barbara, 1966, 1978
    - Guggenheim, Peggy, 1940-76, n.d. (Box 31, Folder 625)
    - Guérin, Daniel, 1959-60 (Box 31, Folder 626)
    - Gutovska, Maria, 1940 (Box 31, Folder 627)
      See also: Series XI, Personal Papers - École bilingue de Neuilly - Correspondence, Box 57 folder 1331
    - "H" general, 1939-85 (Box 31, Folder 628)
    - Hallier, Jean-Edern
      See: Tel Quel, Box 37 folder 791
    - Harry N. Abrams, N.V., 1957-62 (Box 31, Folder 629)
      [includes letters from Pierre
      Courthion to Maria Jolas]
    - Hart, Clive, 1959-63 (Box 31, Folder 630)
    - Havet, Jacques, 1954, n.d. (Box 31, Folder 631)
    - Hayman, David, 1950, 1957
    - Henle, James
      See: Vanguard Press, Box 37 folder 807
    - Herring, Philip, 1980-82 (Box 32, Folder 632)
    - Hessel, Stéphane, 1941 Apr 13
    - Hirshman, André, 1942 Sep 8 (Box 32, Folder 633)
    - Hirshman, Henriette, 1942-51
    - Hoek, Kees van, 1949-54 (Box 32, Folder 634)
    - Horner, Fanny, 1965, n.d. (Box 32, Folder 635)
    - Houghton Mifflin Co., 1954 Aug 18
    - Howard, Richard
    - Huebsch, B. W., 1941-52 (Box 32, Folder 636)
    - Humphrey, Martha, 1941-61, n.d. (Box 32, Folder 637)
    - Hutchinson, Mary, 1961 (Box 32, Folder 638)
    - "I" general, 1965, n.d. (Box 32, Folder 639)
    - Illouz, Claire, 1962-65, n.d. (Box 32, Folder 640)
    - Illouz, Frédéric, 1959-62, n.d. (Box 32, Folder 641)
    - Inghelbrecht, D. E., 1939, 1942, n.d. (Box 32, Folder 642)
    - Inghelbrecht, Germaine, 1953, 1965, n.d.
    - Institute of Irish Studies, 1970-71 (Box 32, Folder 643)
    - Irish Times
      See also: Arthur Power, Box 36 folder 749
    - Irwin, Don, 1952, 1955, n.d. (Box 32, Folder 644)
    - Irwin, Edith, 1972 May 25
    - Irwin, Laetitia, 1935-59
    - Irwin, Wally, 1947-52, n.d.
    - Ischlondsky, Dorin, 1950, 1952 (Box 32, Folder 645)
    - "J" general, 1941-80 (Box 32, Folder 646)
    - Jackson, William A., 1941 (Box 32, Folder 647)
    - Jacob, Louis, 1954-55, n.d.
    - Jankélévich, Vladimir, n.d.
    - Jaryc, Augusta, 1940-60, n.d. (Box 32, Folder 648)
    - Jaulin, Robert, 1972 Mar 22
    - John Calder Publishers, Ltd., 1961-85 (Box 32, Folder 649-51)
    - John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation, 1954 (Box 32, Folder 652)
    - Jolas, Armand, 1939-81
    - Jolas, Betsy, 1960-76, n.d. (Box 32, Folder 653)
    - Jolas, Eugène, 1938-44 (Box 32, Folder 654-56)
    - Jolas, Eugène, 1945-51, n.d. (Box 33, Folder 657-61)
    - Jolas, Eugène [nephew], 1961 Jul 17 (Box 33, Folder 662)
    - Jolas, Helen, 1951-55, n.d. (Box 33, Folder 663)
    - Jolas, Helène, 1950-51
    - Jolas, Jacques, 1941-56, n.d. (Box 33, Folder 664)
    - Jolas, Marie Louise, 1947 (Box 33, Folder 665)
    - Jolas, Pierre, 1946 Oct 14
    - Jolas, Tina, 1978, n.d. (Box 33, Folder 666)
    - Joyce, George [Georgio], 1935-66, n.d. (Box 33, Folder 667)
    - Joyce, James, 1937-41 (Box 33, Folder 668)
    - Joyce, Nora, 1937-49 (Box 33, Folder 669)
    - Joyce, Stanislaus, 1950-51 (Box 33, Folder 670)
      [includes typescripts of "Open
      Letter to Dr. Oliver Gogarty" by
      Stanislaus Joyce and "James Joyce's
      Dublin" by Patricia Hutchins]
    - Joyce, Stephen, 1973, 1977, n.d. (Box 33, Folder 671)
      [includes letter from Peter du Sautoy
      to Stephen Joyce]
    - "K" general, 1937-79 (Box 33, Folder 672)
    - Kahnweiler, Daniel-Henry, 1959, n.d. (Box 33, Folder 673)
    - Kain, Louise, 1951 Apr 1
    - Kain, Richard, 1949-78, n.d.
    - Kandinsky, Wassily, 1937 Feb 1 (Box 33, Folder 674)
    - Kastor, Robert, 1940-63, n.d.
    - Kearney, Richard, 1979-84, n.d. (Box 33, Folder 675)
    - Kennedy, John F., 1963 (Box 33, Folder 676)
    - Kenner, Hugh, 1977 (Box 33, Folder 677)
    - Klopfer, Donald, 1940, 1981 (Box 34, Folder 678)
    - Knowlson, James, 1971-87 (Box 34, Folder 679)
      [includes photocopy of letter by
      Samuel Beckett, 1958 Apr 16]
    - Kraus Reprint Corporation, 1966-73 (Box 34, Folder 680)
    - Kunstmuseum Luzern, 1949 (Box 34, Folder 681)
    - "L" general, 1940-76 (Box 34, Folder 682)
    - Lainé, Minette, 1949 (Box 34, Folder 683)
    - Lainé, Stella, 1951-52, n.d.
    - Lacan, Jacques, 1954 (Box 34, Folder 684)
    - Lacan, Sylvia, 1956 Sep 5
    - Lacroix, Jean, 1954 Oct 29
    - Lalou, René, 1958 Oct 21
    - Laughlin, James, 1942 Apr 21
    - Le Clercq, Edith, 1952, n.d. (Box 34, Folder 685)
    - Le Clercq, Jacques, 1952, 1955
    - Lee, Anne, 1941-46, n.d. (Box 34, Folder 686)
    - Lefort, Claude, 1975 (Box 34, Folder 687)
    - Lehman, John
    - Lehmann-Haupt, Christopher, 1971-72
    - Léon, Jane, 1939-40, n.d. (Box 34, Folder 688)
    - Léon, Lucie [Lucie Noël], 1939-72, n.d. (Box 34, Folder 689)
      See also: Series X, Subject Files - Joyce, James - Birthday Tribute, Box 51 folder 1158
    - Léon, Paul, 1934-40
      See also: Series XI, Personal Papers - École bilingue de Neuilly, Box 57 folder 1331
    - Lescure, Jean, 1956 Nov 27 (Box 34, Folder 690)
    - Les Lettres Nouvelles, 1961-66
      See also: Maurice Nadeau, Box 35 folder 721
      See also: Genevieve Serreau, Box 37, folder 776
    - Letouzey, Yvonne, 1950-51 (Box 34, Folder 690a)
    - Lévi-Strauss, Claude, 1945-46 (Box 34, Folder 691)
      See also: Robert Parker, Box 35 folder 735
    - Lewis, Thomas S. W., 1973 (Box 34, Folder 692)
      [includes photocopy of letter from
      Eugène Jolas to Hart Crane, 1927]
    - Leyris, Pierre, 1947-65, n.d. (Box 34, Folder 693)
      See also: X, A Quarterly Review, Box 38, folder 819
    - Library Journal, 1977 (Box 34, Folder 694)
    - Life Magazine, 1943 Oct 20 (Box 34, Folder 695)
    - Lobbenberg, Marion
    - Loraux, Nicole, 1978, n.d. (Box 34, Folder 696)
    - Lunel, Armand, 1958
    - "M" general, 1937-79, n.d. (Box 34, Folder 697-98)
    - MacBride, Sean, 1949-50 (Box 34, Folder 699)
    - McCarthy, Mary, 1969, 1979
    - McCarville, Eileen, 1973, 1975
    - McCollough, Colleen, 1951-52
    - McDonald, Betsy [mother of Maria Jolas], 1935 Jul 22 (Box 34, Folder 700)
    - McDonald, Cornelia, 1942, 1952 (Box 34, Folder 701)
    - McDonald, Donald, 1935-65, n.d. (Box 34, Folder 702-06)
    - MacDonald, Dwight, 1959-60 (Box 34, Folder 707)
    - McDonald, Eloise, 1937-42
    - McDonald, Hunter, 1951 May 29
    - McDonald, Josie, 1952-65, n.d. (Box 34, Folder 708)
    - McMillan, Dougald, 1966-72 (Box 35, Folder 709)
      See also: Writings of Others
    - Maddox, Brenda, 1985 Sep 11
    - Madaule, Jacques, n.d.
    - Magalaner, Marvin, 1958-59
    - Mandel, Salomé, 1944, n.d. (Box 35, Folder 710)
    - Marienstras, Elise, 1975, 1978, n.d.
    - Martin-Chauffier, Louis, 1958 Oct 23
    - Mascolo, Dionys
    - Masson, André, 1935-59, n.d. (Box 35, Folder 711)
    - Masson, Rose, 1954, n.d.
    - Matisse, Amélie, 1941-45 (Box 35, Folder 712)
    - Matisse, Henri, 1935-50
    - Matisse, Pierre, 1951
    - Matthews, Jackson, 1959 Jul 8 (Box 35, Folder 713)
    - Matthias, Blanche, 1952 May 31
    - Mauriac, Claude, 1960, n.d.
    - Mayer, Peter
    - Mayoux, Jean Jacques, 1954-68, n.d.
    - Menni, Albert, 1955[?] (Box 35, Folder 714)
    - Mercier, Gilis, 1982-83
    - Mercure de France, 1950-62
    - Merton, Thomas, n.d. (Box 35, Folder 715)
    - Minder, Robert, 1947-56, n.d.
    - Miró, Joan, 1939
    - Monaghan, May, 1965-66 (Box 35, Folder 716)
    - Monro, F. Lionel, 1941-67 (Box 35, Folder 717)
    - Monro, Saw & Co.
      See: Monro, F. Lionel, Box 35 folder 717
    - Montiegel, Robert, 1977-78 (Box 35, Folder 718)
    - Morize, André, 1943 (Box 35, Folder 719)
    - "N" general, 1941-85 (Box 35, Folder 720)
      [includes David Norris]
    - Nadeau, Maurice, 1964, 1966, n.d. (Box 35, Folder 721)
    - New Directions, 1959-60 (Box 35, Folder 722)
      See also: James Laughlin, Box 34 folder 684
    - New York Herald Tribune, 1951, 1959 (Box 35, Folder 723)
      [signed by Virgil Thomson?]
    - New York Times, 1947, 1964 (Box 35, Folder 724)
    - Nicholson, Robert, 1979-80 (Box 35, Folder 725)
    - Niemeyer, Carl, 1974 (Box 35, Folder 726)
    - Noufflard, Berthe, 1950-52
    - Noyes, Alfred, 1941
    - Noël, Lucie
      See: Léon, Lucie, Box 34 folder 689
    - "O" general, 1940-81 (Box 35, Folder 727)
    - O Mordha, Sean, 1981-82 (Box 35, Folder 728)
    - Oppenheimer, RObet, 1957 Feb 4
    - Orion Press, 1960-68 (Box 35, Folder 729-32)
      See also: A. Will, Box 38 folder 817
    - Ortleib, Madeleine, 1940 (Box 35, Folder 733)
    - "P" general, 1940-80 (Box 35, Folder 734)
      [includes Simone Piel]
    - Pantheon Books
      See: Bollingen Series, Box 28 folder 539
    - Paris, Jean, 1957 Dec 1 (Box 35, Folder 735)
    - Parker, Robert, 1950-66, n.d.
    - Partisan Review, n.d. (Box 35, Folder 736)
    - Paulding, C. G., 1942, 1957
    - Pearson, Norman Holmes, 1942 Oct 5 (Box 36, Folder 737)
    - Pelorson, Georges, 1939-40
    - Pelorson, Marcelle, 1940-46
    - Pemberton, Cornelia, 1944-65, n.d. (Box 36, Folder 738-39)
    - Pemberton, Kenny, 1965 (Box 36, Folder 740)
    - Pemberton, W. D'Urban, n.d. (Box 36, Folder 741)
    - Peter, Madeline, 1947-65 (Box 36, Folder 742)
    - Peter Nevill, Ltd., 1955 (Box 36, Folder 743)
    - Peyre, Henri, 1960 Feb 10
    - Phillips, Ewan, 1949-50 (Box 36, Folder 744)
    - Phul, Ruth von, 1962-63 (Box 36, Folder 745)
    - Pillsbury, Henry
      See: Series X, Subject Files - Joyce, James - Symposia, Box 55 folder 1279
    - Pitoëff, Varvara, 1942 Sep 24
    - Ponizowski, Eugénie, 1939-40 (Box 36, Folder 746)
    - Potts, Willard, 1975-79 (Box 36, Folder 747)
    - Pound, Dorothy
      See: Huebsch, B. W., Box 32 folder 636
    - Powell, Dawn, 1951-52, n.d. (Box 36, Folder 748)
    - Power, Arthur, 1949, 1951 (Box 36, Folder 749)
      See also: Irish Times, Box 32 folder 643
    - Prescott, Joseph, 1951-55 (Box 36, Folder 750)
    - Princeton University Press, 1978-79 (Box 36, Folder 751)
    - Pryce-Jones, Alan
      See: Times Literary Supplement, Box 37 folder 794
    - Queneau, Raymond, 1939-40 (Box 36, Folder 752)
    - "R" general, 1939-77 (Box 36, Folder 753)
    - Rahv, Philip
    - Ramnoux, Clémence, 1955, 1984, n.d. (Box 36, Folder 754)
    - Random House, Inc., 1972
      See also: Donald Klopfer, Box 34 folder 678
    - Rasquin, Marthe, 1939-40 (Box 36, Folder 755)
    - Rasquin, Roger, 1939-50, n.d.
    - Reavey, George, n.d. (Box 36, Folder 756)
    - Rebérioux, Madeleine, 1986 Mar 9
    - Reichel, Käthe, 1956-67
    - Renée Spodheim Associates, 1958-59 (Box 36, Folder 757)
    - Rexroth-Kern, Iringard, 1955 (Box 36, Folder 758)
    - Rice, Elmer, 1941 Mar 7 (Box 36, Folder 759)
    - Rinehart & Co., 1949
    - Rodgers, W. R., 1949-50
      See also: British Broadcasting Corporation, Box 28 folder 544
    - Roelli, Ximena de Angulo, 1942-84, n.d. (Box 36, Folder 760)
    - Rogers, W. G., 1964-66 (Box 36, Folder 761)
    - Rose, Danis, 1973, 1977 (Box 36, Folder 762)
    - Rougemont, Denis de, 1946 Apr 29
    - Roux, Dominique de, 1962 Jul 23 (Box 36, Folder 763)
    - Rovan, Joseph, 1956, n.d.
    - Roy, Claude, n.d.
    - Roy Publishers, 1944
    - Rumold, Rainer, 1978-79 (Box 36, Folder 764)
    - "S" general, 1939-84, n.d. (Box 36, Folder 765-67)
      [includes Robert Sage]
    - Saillet, Maurice, 1975 Mar 19 (Box 36, Folder 768)
    - Sauret, André
    - Sarraute, Nathalie, 1952-77, n.d.
      See also: Series IX, Translations, Box 43 folder 959
    - Schaurek, Eileen, 1949 (Box 36, Folder 769)
    - Schebeko, M.
    - Scheler, Lucien, 1957 Jan 5
    - Schimanski, Stefan, 1950
    - Schneider, Pierre, 1952-62 (Box 36, Folder 770)
    - Schuwer, Camille, 1940, n.d.
      [includes poem by Camille Schuwer:
      "Ulysse: In Memoriam Joyce"]
    - Schuwer, Philippe, 1949, 1952
    - Scott, Bonnie, 1977, 1982 (Box 36, Folder 771)
    - Scott, Michael, 1985 (Box 37, Folder 772)
    - Seabury Press, 1973 (Box 37, Folder 773)
    - Seidenmann, Stella, 1959-63 (Box 37, Folder 774)
    - Seldes, Gilbert, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 775)
    - Selz, Jean, 1960-61
    - Senn, Fritz, 1966-80 (Box 37, Folder 776)
    - Serreau, Geneviève, 1959 Dec 30
    - Silpikula, L., 1940 (Box 37, Folder 777)
    - Slocum, John J., 1941-50, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 778)
    - The Society of Authors, 1960-66 (Box 37, Folder 779)
    - Sollers, Philippe, 1979 Nov 3
    - Solveen, Henri, 1952-53 (Box 37, Folder 780)
    - Solveen, Marthe, 1958-59
    - Sonnier, George, 1954-57 (Box 37, Folder 781)
    - Soupault, Marie-Louise, 1939-54 (Box 37, Folder 782)
    - Soupault, Philippe, 1965 Mar 2
    - Sowerwine, Charles, 1974-80 (Box 37, Folder 783)
    - Spire, André
    - Sprigge, Cecil, 1957 Nov 5 (Box 37, Folder 784)
    - Sprigge, Elizabeth, 1957
    - Sprigge, Sylvia, 1956-61
    - Staley, Thomas, 1973-74 (Box 37, Folder 785)
    - Steloff, Frances, 1939-83 (Box 37, Folder 786)
      See also: Gotham Book Mart, Box 31 folder 622
    - Stern, James, 1951-84 (Box 37, Folder 787)
    - Stuart, Ruth, 1947, 1952 (Box 37, Folder 788)
    - Suttle, Eileen, 1962-65 (Box 37, Folder 789)
    - Sweeney, James Johnson, 1941, n.d.
    - "T" general, 1939-81, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 790)
    - Tel Quel, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 791)
    - Tenzer, Anita
    - Terrier-Santans, Marthe de, 1940, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 792)
    - Therèse [Jolas family cook], 1940, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 793)
    - Thompson, John H., 1941
    - Times Literary Supplement, 1959 (Box 37, Folder 794)
      See also: Pryce-Jones, Alan, Box 36 folder 751
    - Times Publishing Co., 1959-60
    - Tompkins, Lionel, 1950-62 (Box 37, Folder 795)
    - [EMPTY FOLDER] (Box 37, Folder 796)
    - Traizet, Thérèse, 1939-40 (Box 37, Folder 797)
    - Trianon Press, 1964 (Box 37, Folder 798)
    - Trotha, Marguerite, 1955-59 (Box 37, Folder 799)
    - Tzara, Tristan, 1949 Nov 19
    - "U" general, 1940-62 (Box 37, Folder 800)
    - Ungaretti, Giuseppe, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 801)
    - University of Chicago Press, 1941, 1971
    - University of Illinois Press, 1983 (Box 37, Folder 802)
      [includes note from Bobby
      Franckenstein]
    - Untermeyer, Jean Starr, 1949-52, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 803)
      [includes printed poem "A Bunch of
      Sweet-Peas]
    - "V" general, 1939-76 (Box 37, Folder 804)
    - Vail, Sharon, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 805)
    - Vailland, Genevieve, 1940, n.d.
    - Valentin, Curt, 1952 Jun 12
      See also: Buchholz Gallery, Box 29 folder 547
    - Vallotton, M. J., 1940-41 (Box 37, Folder 806)
    - Vanguard Press, 1949-53 (Box 37, Folder 807)
    - Ventadour, Fanny, 1940-74 (Box 37, Folder 808)
    - Vercors, 1958 Feb 1
    - Vercors, Rita, 1954 Oct 20
    - Verlag Gerd Hatje, 1957, 1963 (Box 37, Folder 809)
    - Vidal-Naquet, Denis, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 810)
    - Vidal-Naquet, Jacques, 1976, n.d.
    - Vidal-Naquet, Pierre, 1974-84, n.d.
    - "W" general, 1941-79, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 811-12)
    - Wahl, Jean, 1947-61, n.d. (Box 38, Folder 813)
    - Wahl, Marcelle, 1949
    - Walteville, J. de, 1940 (Box 38, Folder 814)
    - Weideman, Hugh
    - Weideman, Stella
    - Weidlé, Wladimir, 1949 May 4
    - Weightman, John, 1948-64 (Box 38, Folder 815)
    - Wilder, Thornton, 1940-41 (Box 38, Folder 816)
    - Will, A., 1960-63 (Box 38, Folder 817)
      See also: Orion Press, Box 35 folder 729
    - Wilson, Edmund, 1941 (Box 38, Folder 818)
    - Wright, David
      See: X, A Quarterly Review, Box 38 folder 819
    - X, A Quarterly Review, 1959-61 (Box 38, Folder 819)
      [includes Pierre Leyris]
    - Zinke, Martin, 1950 Jun 23 (Box 38, Folder 820)
    - Unidentified - Letters by Maria Jolas, 1941-73, n.d. (Box 38, Folder 821)
    - Unidentified - Cards, ca. 1939-73 (Box 38, Folder 822)
    - Unidentified - Condolence letters, 1952 (Box 38, Folder 823)
    - Unidentified - Friends and Family, ca. 1939-65 (Box 38, Folder 824-25)
    - Unidentified - Grandchildren (Box 38, Folder 826)
    - Unidentified - Researchers, 1958-86 (Box 38, Folder 827)
    - Empty envelopes, 1940-82 (Box 38, Folder 828)
  - THIRD PARTY
    - Alexeïeff, Svet from Jolas, Betsy, 1943 Jan 1 (Box 38, Folder 829)
    - Ammerman, Richard from Lucie Léon, 1957 Dec 3
      [includes note from Maria Jolas]
    - Andlauer, Philippe from l'abbé Pierre, 1946 Apr 2
    - Boyle, Kay from Pol, Heinz, 1942 Jan 23
    - Cole, George C. from Whipple J. van H., 1944 Jan 3
    - Delaney, Jim from Klarnet, Phil, 1945 Apr 24 (Box 38, Folder 830)
    - Dillenschneider, Maria from Dillenschneider, Celestin, n.d.
    - Duthuit, Georges (Box 38, Folder 831)
      - from College Art Association, 1941 May 20
      - from Daniel, Char-, n.d.
      - from Duthuit, Marguerite, 1945
      - from Glas, Emil, 1945 Jul 13
      - from Matisse, Amélie, 1944, 1950
      - from Tulane University, 1941 Apr 7
      - from Van Altena, Edward, 1941 May 15
      - from Virginia Museum of Fine Arts, 1944 Jan
    - Duthuit, Marguerite from Jolas, Tina, 1943 Apr 16 (Box 38, Folder 832)
    - Ellmann, Richard from Giedion-Welcker, Carola, 1954 Jun 28
    - Gilbert, Stuart from Léon, Paul
      See: Subject Files - Joyce, James - Exhibitions - La Hune - Catalog, Box 53 folder 1211
    - Huebsch, B. W. from Weaver, Harriet, 1945 Dec 30
    - Hull, Cordell (Box 38, Folder 833)
      - from Maritain, Jacques, 1941 May 27
    - Illouz, Gabriel
      - from Illouz, Frédéric, 1962 Apr 16
      - from Tichy, H., 1962
    - Jolas, Betsy (Box 38, Folder 834)
      - from Duthuit, George, 1941
      - from Finsler, Helène, 1940 Sep 28
      - from Plé-Cassaude, Simone, 1949
      - from Unidentified, 1943, n.d.
    - Jolas, Celestin (Box 38, Folder 835)
      - from Unidentified, 1955 Aug 19
    - Jolas, Christine
      - from Jolas, Jacques, n.d.
    - Jolas, Helène
      - from Jo, 1944 Aug 26
    - Jolas, Jacques
      - from Fanning, 1927 Oct 27
      - from Jolas, Gyda, 1928 Apr 5
    - Jolas, Tina (Box 38, Folder 836)
      - from Dillenschneider, Maria, 1945 Nov 15
      - from Duthuit, Claude, n.d.
      - from Duthuit, Georges, 1941
      - from Illouz, Frédèric, 1958 Aug 11
    - Joyce, George [Giorgio] (Box 38, Folder 837)
      - from Gheerbrandt, Bernard
    - Joyce, James
      - from Brauchbar, Edmund, 1938 Sep 22
    - Joyce, Nora
      - from Sax, Sylvia, 1939 Jun 20
    - Joyce, Stephen (Box 38, Folder 838)
      - from Greaves, Richard L., n.d.
    - Matisse, Pierre
      - from Matisse, Amélie, 1944 Aug 12
    - Monro, F. Lionel (Box 38, Folder 839)
      - from Joyce, Nora, n.d.
    - Pickett, Mr.
      - from Maritain, Jacques, 1941 May 27
    - Roosevelt, Eleanor
      - from Maritain, Jacques, 1941 May 27
    - Sternberger, Dr. (Box 38, Folder 840)
      - from Mann, Thomas, 1946 Mar 19
    - United States Embassy
      - from Joyce, James, 1940 Sep 5
    - Wilder, Thornton
      - from Fickler, Edward B., 1941 May 1
    - Unidentified (Box 38, Folder 841)
      - from Jolas, Tina, 1943 Apr 16
    - Unidentified (Box 38, Folder 842)
      - from Duthuit, Georges, 1945
      - from Wahl, Jean, n.d.
    - Unidentified - Others
      - "Diana", 1947
      - "Pierrette", n.d.
- Maria Jolas - Writings, 1883-1983; Series VIII; 1.75; (4 boxes)
  Series VIII is divided into nine subseries. Material within each subseries is arranged alphabetically.
  - ARTICLES AND ESSAYS
    - [American Sentiment and World War II], typescript, corrected (Box 39, Folder 843)
    - "Americans in Paris," typescript carbon, corrected and printed version, Times Literary Supplement, 1959 Mar 20 (Box 39, Folder 844)
    - "Atlantic Voyage - 1946," typescript carbon (Box 39, Folder 845)
    - "A Bloomlein for Sam," typescript carbon, [1966] (Box 39, Folder 846)
    - Comments on "Long Range Policy Guidance for France," typescript carbon, corrected, 1944 Jun 11 (Box 39, Folder 847)
    - [Corporal Punishment in Schools], typescript corrected, n.d. (Box 39, Folder 848)
    - [on Critique ], typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 39, Folder 849)
    - "Critique de la conférence de M. l'Abbé Boulier au Collège philosophique," typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 39, Folder 850)
    - "Le débarquement en Normandie vu d'Amérique," printed version Journal de Genève, 1944 Jun 16 (Box 39, Folder 851)
    - [De Gaulle and the Fourth Republic], typescript carbon, corrected (Box 39, Folder 852)
    - "L'élégant chemin de James Joyce," excerpt from Lettres Nouvelles
      - Printed copy, [1961] (Box 39, Folder 853)
      - Clipping, 1961 Oct
    - "L'enseignement bilingue," typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 39, Folder 854)
    - "La femme américaine et la maison," typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 39, Folder 855)
    - "French Literature," Encyclopedia Britannica, typescript carbons, 1942-51 (Box 39, Folder 856)
    - [French Occupation and Writers], typescript, corrected (Box 39, Folder 857)
    - "Gordonstoun," typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 39, Folder 858)
    - "Une grande Française vient de disparaître," [obituary of Rita Levy-Savoye] typescript carbon, corrected (Box 39, Folder 859)
    - "How Joyce loved a traditional holiday," typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 39, Folder 860)
    - "Introduction to a Possible Book on Education," holograph [with clipping], n.d. (Box 39, Folder 861)
    - "'I Write', said Joyce"
      - typescript, French, 1975 Jun 18 (Box 39, Folder 862)
      - printed booklet, French, 1979
      - printed booklet, English, 1975
    - "Joyce en 1939-40" (Box 39, Folder 863)
      - Drafts, typescripts, corrected, n.d.
      - printed version, Mercure de France, 1950 May 1 (Box 39, Folder 864)
      - English translation [abridged], typescript carbon, corrected, [1956] (Box 39, Folder 865)
    - "The Joyce I Knew and the Woman Around Him," The Crane Bag, page proofs [with letter from Colin McCabe], 1982 (Box 39, Folder 866)
    - "Joyce's Friend Jolas," A James Joyce Miscellany, [pages], 1957 (Box 39, Folder 867)
    - "Literary Prizes - France" Encyclopedia Britannica, holograph, typescript and page proofs, [1949-51?] (Box 39, Folder 868)
    - "The Little Known Paul Léon"
      - Draft, typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 39, Folder 869)
      - Printed copy from A James Joyce Miscellany, second series
    - "La mère, espoir des nations," typescript carbon, corrected [with brochure], 1947 Apr 27 (Box 39, Folder 870)
    - "Modern Schools," typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 39, Folder 871)
    - [Notes on the History of War], n.d. (Box 39, Folder 872)
    - "Paris" Encyclopedia Britannica, typescript carbons, corrected and page proofs, 1949-51 (Box 39, Folder 873)
    - "Réponse à l'enquête: Croyez-vous à la paix?," typescript carbon, 1955 (Box 39, Folder 874)
    - Response to "Why is There No Native American Art" by Georges Duthuit, typescript, 1947 (Box 39, Folder 875)
    - [Review of Les guerres que j'ai vues by Gertrude Stein], notes and clippings, 1980 (Box 39, Folder 876)
    - "La Rue - Ann Petry" La géographie humaine, typescript carbon, 1949 Feb (Box 39, Folder 877)
    - "Some Thought of a Very Old Woman," typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 39, Folder 878)
    - "Tea in (Paris) China," holograph, corrected, 1974 Apr 4 (Box 39, Folder 879)
    - "Theatre - France" Encyclopedia Britannica, typescript carbons and page proofs, 1949-51, n.d. (Box 39, Folder 880)
    - "Use and Abuse of the Symbol," typescript and holograph, corrected (Box 39, Folder 881)
    - "When I first arrived in Paris..."," holograph, n.d. (Box 39, Folder 882)
    - "With Love for Europe," typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 39, Folder 883)
    - Miscellaneous fragments, n.d. (Box 39, Folder 884)
  - AUTOBIOGRAPHY
    - Audiotape transcripts
      - Transcripts, n.d. (Box 39, Folder 885)
    - Correspondence
      - Correspondence, 1982-83 (Box 39, Folder 886)
    - Photographs